A Guide to the Union Envelope Company records, 1892-2000
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Union Envelope Company records, 1892-2000
The Library of Virginia
52444
5.38 cubic feet and 10 boxes and 3 volumes
Union Envelope Company
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Elizabeth Shumaker, Richmond, Virginia.
Historical Information
Johnson Duplex Envelope Company was founded in Richmond, Virginia, 1902 to manufacture church collection envelopes. In 1903, the company was purchased by Richmond businessmen who expanded its envelope manufacturing and changed the name of the company to Union Envelope. A 1912 fire destroyed the company's plant, but the business relocated and continued to expand. Union Envelope eventually outgrew its facilities and opened a new plant in 1951. In 1954, Union Envelope opened a second plant in Birmingham, Alabama. The Birmingham plant saw expansion in 1964 and 1974. Union Envelope merged with Hammermill Paper Company in 1960, becoming a part of that company. Another plant was opened in Dallas, Texas, 1972 and expanded in 1978. Union Envelope became part of International Paper in 1986 when that company bought Hammermill Paper. Union Envelope closed 31 October 1994.
Scope and Content
Records, 1892-2000 (bulk 1909-1990), of the Union Envelope Company of Richmond, Virginia, consisting of account books, advertisements, charter and bylaws, correspondence, financial records, histories, meeting minutes, obituaries, photographs, plans, price lists and related papers concerning the operation of the Union Envelope Company. Collections also includes ephemera such as awards, hats, mugs, and promotional materials. One volume contains what seems to be accounts, 1892, for Old Dominion Iron and Nail Works Company.
Contents List
- Series I: Records, 1892-2000., Extent: 3 volumes and 2 boxes. (Box 1-2)
  - Old Dominion Iron and Nail Works account book and Union Envelope Company inventory ledger, 1892 and undated. (Volume 1)
  - Union Envelope account book, 1909-1917. (Volume 2)
  - Union Envelope account book, 1918-1927. (Volume 3)
  - History of Union Envelope Company, 1969. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - History of Union Envelope Company, 1972. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - History of Union Envelope Company, 1974, 1979. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - History of Union Envelope Company, 1988. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Charter and bylaws, 1927. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Board minutes and related papers, 3 May 1946-16 January 1948. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Board minutes and related papers, 2 February 1948-20 January 1950. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Board minutes and related papers, 1 February 1950-30 October 1953. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Board minutes and related papers, 1 February 1954-22 February 1957. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Board minutes and related papers, 3 April 1957-10 October 1960. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Board of directors meeting--authorization, 12 December 1952. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Board of directors organization meeting minutes, 31 January 1958. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Board of directors organization meeting minutes, 30 January 1959. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Proxies for annual meeting of stockholders, 30 January 1959. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Board of directors meeting minutes, 20 March 1959. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Board of directors organization meeting minutes, 29 January 1960. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Board of directors meeting minutes, 16 August 1960. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Board of directors meeting resolution, 6 September 1960. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Board of directors meeting minutes, 10 October 1960. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Special stockholders meeting, 10 October 1960. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - List of shareholders, no date. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Financial statements, ca. 1958, 1959. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Payroll sheets, May 1940. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Monthly sales report, 8 January 1991. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Customer service packet, ca. 1980s. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Green Stamp Act of 1975, 1975. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Union Envelope and Dillard Paper Company: 50 Golden Years Together, 1976. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Advertisements. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Notebook on paper stock. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Union Envelope price list no. 7, no date. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Union Envelope price list, 1950. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Union converting small roll specialists--rolls for calculators, adding machines, etc., October 1979. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Count sheet, no date. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Envelopes and related items, 1929, no date. (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Papers, 1958. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Papers, 1959. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Papers, 1960. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Papers, 1971. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Papers, 1975. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Papers, 1978. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Papers, 1979-1980. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Papers, 1986-1987. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Papers (including information on William H. Palmer, 1867-1946), 1988. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Papers, 2000. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Obituaries: William H. Palmer, Isaac L. Rheutan, and Richard D. Rheutan, 1945, 1946, 1977. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Worth-Higgins and Associates photograph and layout for Union Envelope. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Union Envelope blank notepad. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Hammermill Paper Company. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - United States Envelope Company price list, ca. 1904. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - United States Envelope Company price list no. 13, 1914. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - United States Envelope Company price list no. 26, no date. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - United States Envelope Company price list no. 29, no date. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - United States Envelope Company price list no. 35, no date. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - United States Envelope Company price list no. 44, 1918. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - United States Envelope Company price list no. 47, November 1919. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - United States Envelope Company price list no. 49, April 1920. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - United States Envelope Company price list no. 50, July 1920. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - United States Envelope Company price list no. 51, September 1920. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - United States Envelope Company price list no. 52, November 1920. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - United States Envelope Company price list no. 55, July 1921. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - United States Envelope Company price list no. 58, November 1922. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - W. H. Hill Envelope Company price list no. 6, no date. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - W. H. Hill Envelope Company price list no. 7, no date. (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Landenberger's Paper Equivalentor. (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Hunt Beinfang construction paper samples. (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Pages with numbered lines, no information. (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Series II: Photographs., Extent: 1 box. (Box 3)
  - Spotswood Hall. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Robert Kyle. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - R. O. Mann, 16 January 1951. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - William H. Palmer. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Richard D. Rheutan. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Photographs (and negatives), 1946-1950. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, 1957. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, 1960-1961. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Berkley Machine Company, Kansas City, Missouri, 14 December 1968. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Photograph, November 1980. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Slides (and negatives), 1981. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Photographs, January 1986. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Company photographs (5 copies). (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - National Quality Month (with negatives) by Little Joe Wiesenfeld Company, 1988. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - National Quality Month and related correspondence, 1988, 1989 (included earlier staff photograph now located in oversize). (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Photographs and negatives, ca. 1980s,. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Old plant (after fire in 1912?). (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Plant photographs. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Photographs of plants located in Birmingham, Alabama, and Grand Prairie (near Dallas), Texas. (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Delivery truck, 1926. (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Personnel at work. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Employee at machine. (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Champion S. O. Machine. (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Photographs of machinery by J. A. Williams. (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Machinery photographs. (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Machiney photographs. (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Machinery photographs (and negatives). (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Machinery photographs (color) (and negatives). (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Oversized negatives. (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Miscellaneous materials related to photographs. (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Series III: Ephemera,., Extent: 5 boxes. (Box 4-8)
  - EMAA Industry Safety Award, 1991. (Box 4)
  - EMAA Industry Safety Leader, 1992. (Box 5)
  - EMAA Industry Safety Leader, 1993. (Box 5)
  - The Public Printer's Certificate of Appreciation, 1985. (Box 5)
  - Union Envelope cap. (Box 6)
  - UE cap. (Box 6)
  - Union Envelope mug. (Box 6)
  - Old Colony Envelope (International Paper) letter openers. (Box 6)
  - Union Envelope Introduces Union Express. (Box 7)
  - U, E, and C letters. (Box 8)
- Oversized materials., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 9-10)
  Materials removed from other parts of the collection due to their size are located in these boxes. Markers in the collection provide box and folder location.